Zika fever:
حمّى زيكا
our newest dread disease.
أحدث أمراضنا المخيفة.
What is it? Where'd it come from?
ما هو؟ ومن أين أتى؟
What do we do about it?
وماذا نفعل حياله؟
Well for most adults, it's a relatively mild disease --
إنه مرض معتدل الخطورة نسبيًا لمعظم الكبار،
a little fever, a little headache, joint pain, maybe a rash.
حمّى خفيفة، وصداع بسيط، وألم في المفاصل، وربما طفح جلدي.
In fact, most people who get it don't even know they've had it.
في الواقع، لا يعرفُ معظم من أصابهم الفيروس أنهم مصابون به.
But the more we find out about the Zika virus
لكن كلما عرفنا أكثر عن فيروس زيكا
the more terrifying it becomes.
كلما أصبح الأمرُ مروعًا أكثر.
For example, doctors have noticed an uptick
على سبيل المثال، لاحظ الأطباء ارتفاعًا
of something called Guillain-Barré syndrome in recent outbreaks.
لشيء يسمى متلازمة (غيلان باريه) في الأمراض المتفشية في الآونة الأخيرة.
In Guillain-Barré, your immune system attacks your nerve cells
تعني متلازمة غيلان باريه أن نظام المناعة لديكم يهاجمُ خلاياكم العصبية
it can partially or even totally paralyze you.
ويمكنها أن تشل حركتكم جزئيًا، أو حتى كليًا.
Fortunately, that's quite rare, and most people recover.
لحسن الحظ، هذا الأمر نادر الحدوث، ويتعافى معظم الناس.
But if you're pregnant when you're infected
لكن إذا حصل وكانت المرأة حاملًا عندما تصاب به
you're at risk of something terrible.
ستكونُ في خطر حدوث شيء مروع.
Indeed, a child with a deformed head.
بالفعل، طفل ذو رأس مشوه.
Here's a normal baby.
هذا طفلٌ طبيعي.
Here's that infant with what's called microcephaly.
هذا رضيع بما يسمى صغر الرأس أو الصَعَل.
a brain in a head that's too small.
يوجد دماغ داخل رأس صغيرة جدًا.
And there's no known cure.
ولا يوجد علاج معروف لذلك.
It was actually doctors in northeastern Brazil
كان في الواقع أطباء منطقة شمال شرق البرازيل
who first noticed, just a year ago, after a Zika outbreak,
هم أول من لاحظوا ذلك، قبل عام واحد فقط، بعد انتشار زيكا،
that there was a peak in the incidence of microcephaly.
بأن هناك ارتفاعًا في حالات صغر الرأس.
It took medical doctors another year
واستغرق الأمر الأطباء عامًا آخر
to be sure that it was caused by the Zika virus,
للتأكد من أنه كان نتيجة فيروس زيكا،
but they're now sure.
لكنهم الآن متأكدون من ذلك.
And if you're a "bring on the evidence" type,
وإذا كنتم مهتمين بالأدلة،
check out this publication.
عليكم قراءة هذه النشرة.
So where did it come from, and how did it get here?
فمن أين أتى المرض، وكيف وصل هنا؟
And it is here.
وإنه هنا.
Like many of our viruses, it came out of Africa,
مثل العديد من الفيروسات التي لدينا، فإنه أتى من أفريقيا،
specifically the Zika forest in Uganda.
ولا سيما من "غابة زيكا من أوغندا".
Researchers at the nearby Yellow Fever Research Institute
فالباحثون قرب "معهد أبحاث الحمى الصفراء"
identified an unknown virus in a monkey in the Zika forest
حددوا فيروسًا غير معروف في قرد في "غابة زيكا"
which is how it got its name.
ومن هنا حصل على اسمه.
The first human cases of Zika fever
والحالات البشرية الأولى لمصابي حمى زيكا
surfaced a few years later in Uganda-Tanzania.
ظهرت بعد سنوات قليلة في (أوغندا-تنزانيا).
The virus then spread through West Africa
ومن ثم انتشر الفيروس عبر غرب أفريقيا
and east through equatorial Asia -- Pakistan, India, Malaysia, Indonesia.
وإلى الشرق من خلال آسيا الإستوائية مثل: باكستان والهند وماليزيا وأندونيسيا.
But it was still mostly in monkeys and, of course, mosquitoes.
لكنه كان لا يزالُ في معظمه في القرود، وبطبيعة الحال في البعوض.
In fact in the 60 years between the time it was first identified in 1947 and 2007
في الواقع، وفي السنوات الستين بين الوقت الذي تم تحديده لأول مرة في عام 1947 و 2007
there were only 13 reported cases of human Zika fever.
تم الإبلاغ فقط عن 13 حالة لحمى زيكا البشرية.
And then something extraordinary happened on the tiny Micronesian Yap islands.
ومن ثم حصل شيء غير عادي في جزر ياب الصغيرة لولايات ميكرونيسيا المتحدة.
There was an outbreak that affected fully 75 percent of the population.
كان هناك انتشارٌ أصاب 75% من السكان.
How did it get there? By air.
كيف وصل هناك؟ عن طريق الجو.
Today we have two billion commercial airline passengers.
لدينا الآن 2 مليار مسافر يستخدمون الخطوط الجوية التجارية.
An infected passenger can board a plane, fly halfway around the world
يمكنُ للأشخاص المصابين ركوب الطائرة، والسفر نصف الطريق حول العالم
before developing symptoms -- if they develop symptoms at all.
قبل بداية ظهور الأعراض، هذا إذا ظهرت الأعراض أصلًا.
Then when they land, the local mosquitoes begin to bite them and spread the fever.
وعندما يهبطون، يبدأ البعوض المحلي في لدغهم ونشر الحمّى.
Zika fever then next surfaced in 2013 in French Polynesia.
ظهرت حمّى زيكا لاحقًا في عام 2013 في بولينزيا الفرنسية.
By December of that year, it was being transmitted locally by the mosquitoes.
وبحلول شهر ديسمبر/كانون أول من العام نفسه، تم نقله محليًا من قبل البعوض.
That led to an explosive outbreak in which almost 30,000 people were affected.
مما أدى إلى انتشاره الكثيف حيث تم إصابة 30,000 شخص تقريبًا.
From there it radiated around the Pacific.
ومن هناك انتشر حول المحيط الهادي.
There were outbreaks in the Cook Islands, in New Caledonia,
كان هناك تفشيٌ في جزر كوك، وفي كاليدونيا الجديدة،
in Vanuatu, in the Solomon Islands
وفي جمهورية فانواتو، وفي جزر سليمان
and almost all the way around to the coast of South America and Easter Island.
وتقريبًا على طول الطريق إلى ساحل أمريكا الجنوبية وجزيرة القيامة.
And then, in early 2015,
وبعد ذلك، وفي أوائل عام 2015،
there was an upsurge of cases of a dengue-like syndrome
كان هناك حالات متزايدة تشبه "متلازمة حمى الضنك"
in the city of Natal in northeastern Brazil.
في مدينة (ناتال) شمال شرق البرازيل.
The virus wasn't dengue, it was Zika, and it spread rapidly --
لم يكن الفيروس "فيروس الضنك" بل كان (زيكا) وقد انتشر بسرعة،
Recife down the coast, a big metropolitan center, soon became the epicenter.
وبسرعة أصبحت (ريسيفي) أسفل الساحل، المدينة الكبيرة المركزية، بؤرة للمرض.
Well people have speculated that it was 2014 World Cup soccer fans
تكهنت الناس أن مشجعي كأس العالم لكرة القدم عام 2014
that brought the virus into the country.
هم من أحضر الفيروس إلى البلاد.
But others have speculated that perhaps it was Pacific Islanders
لكن تكهن البعض الآخر أنه ربما سكان جزر المحيط الهادي
participating in championship canoe races
الذين شاركوا في بطولة مسابقات الزوارق
that were held in Rio that year that brought it in.
التي عقدت في (ريو) تلك السنة هم من جلب الفيروس للبلاد.
Well today, this is only a year later.
واليوم بعد عام فقط.
The virus is being locally transmitted by mosquitoes
تمّ نقل الفيروس محليًا من قبل البعوض
virtually throughout South America, Central America, Mexico
تقريبًا في جميع مناطق جنوب أمريكا، وأمريكا الوسطى، والمكسيك
and the Caribbean Islands
وجزر الكاريبي.
Until this year, the many thousands of cases
حتى هذا العام، بضعة الآلاف من الحالات
that have been diagnosed in the US were contracted elsewhere.
التي تم تشخيصها في أمريكا، تمّ إصابتها في مكانٍ آخر.
But as of this summer, it's being transmitted locally in Miami.
ولكن مع حلول هذا الصيف، تم نقلها محليًا في (ميامي).
It's here.
إنه هنا.
So what do we do about it?
لهذا ماذا نفعلُ حيال ذلك؟
Well, preventing infection
حسنًا، منع العدوى
is either about protecting people or about eliminating the mosquitoes.
يكون إما بحماية الناس أو القضاء على البعوض.
Let's focus on people first.
دعونا أولًا نركزُ على الناس.
You can get vaccinated.
يمكنكم الحصول على التطعيم.
You can not travel to Zika areas.
يمكنكم عدم السفر إلى المناطق الموبوءة بزيكا.
Or you can cover up and apply insect repellent.
أو يمكنكم تغطية أنفسكم ودهن طارد للحشرات.
Getting vaccinated is not an option, because there isn't a vaccine yet
ليس التطعيم خيارًا، لأنه لا يوجد لقاح حتى الآن.
and there probably won't be for a couple of years.
وربما لن يكون لعدة سنوات قادمة.
Staying home isn't a foolproof protection either
وليس البقاء في البيت حماية مضمونة إمّا
because we now know that it can be sexually transmitted.
لأننا عرفنا الآن أنه يمكنُ أن ينتقل عن طريق الاتصال الجنسي.
Covering up and applying insect repellent does work ...
تغطية أنفسكم والدهن بطارد الحشرات يؤدي الغرض
until you forget.
إلى أن تنسوا فعله.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So that leaves the mosquitoes, and here's how we control them now:
إذا لم يتبقى لنا سوى البعوض، وإليكم الآن كيفية السيطرة عليه،
spraying insecticides.
رش المبيدات الحشرية.
The protective gear is necessary because these are toxic chemicals
المعدات الواقية مهمة لأن هذه المبيدات هي مواد كيميائية سامة
that kill people as well as bugs.
تقتلُ الناس كما الحشرات.
Although it does take quite a lot more to kill a person than to kill a bug.
ويستغرقُ الأمر وقتًا أطول لقتل شخص من قتل حشرة.
These are pictures from Brazil and Nicaragua.
هذه صور من البرازيل ونيغاراغوا.
But it looks the same in Miami, Florida.
ولكنها تشبه تمامًا تلك الصور من (ميامي في ولاية فلوريدا).
And we of course can spray insecticides from planes.
ويمكننا بالطبع رش المبيدات الحشرية من الطائرات.
Last summer, mosquito control officials in Dorchester County, South Carolina,
في الصيف الماضي، قام مسؤولو مكافحة البعوض في مقاطعة دورشستر/ ولاية كارولينا الجنوبية
authorized spraying of Naled, an insecticide,
بالسماح برش مبيد الفوسفات العضوي (Naled) مبيد خطير للإنسان والحشرات،
early one morning, as recommended by the manufacturer.
في صباح ذات يوم كما أوصت الشركة المصنّعة.
Later that day, a beekeeper told reporters
وفي وقتٍ لاحق من ذلك اليوم، قالت إحدى مربيات النحل للصحفيين
that her bee yard looked like it had been nuked.
بأن حديقة نحلها بدت وكأنها ضربت بقنبلة نووية.
Oops.
يالا الهول!
Bees are the good guys.
النحل مخلوقات مفيدة.
The citizens of Florida protested, but spraying continued.
احتج مواطنو ولاية فلوريدا، لكن استمر الرش.
Unfortunately, so did the increase in the number of Zika fever cases.
لسوء الحظ، زاد عدد حالات المصابين بزيكا.
That's because insecticides aren't very effective.
لأن المبيدات الحشرية غير فعالة كثيرًا.
So are there any approaches that are perhaps more effective than spraying
هل هناك وسائل أخرى ربما تكون فعالة أكثر من الرش
but with less downsides than toxic chemicals?
لكن بآثار سلبية أقل من المواد الكيميائية السامة؟
I'm a huge fan of biological controls,
أنا من أشد المعجبين بالضوابط البيولوجية،
and I share that view with Rachel Carson, author of "Silent Spring,"
وأتفقُ مع وجهة نظر (راشيل كارسون)، مؤلفة كتاب "الربيع الصامت".
the book that is credited with starting the environmental movement.
الكتاب الذي له الفضل في بداية الحركة البيئية.
In this book she tells the story, as an example,
تقولُ في هذا الكتاب قصة، على سبيل المثال،
of how a very nasty insect pest of livestock
عن كيف أن آفة حشرة سيئة جدًا للثروة الحيوانية
was eliminated in the last century.
تم القضاء عليها في القرن الأخير.
No one knows that extraordinary story today.
لا أحد يعرفُ هذه القصة الرائعة اليوم.
So Jack Block and I, when we were writing an editorial
لذلك عندما أردتُ وجاك بلوك كتابة افتتاحية
about the mosquito problem today, retold that story.
حول مشكلة البعوض اليوم، أعدنا كتابة تلك القصة.
And in capsule form, it's that pupae -- that's the immature form of the insect --
وفي شكل كبسولة، إنها شرنقة، هذا هو الشكل غير الناضج للحشرة،
were irradiated until they were sterile, grown to adulthood
مشعشعة حتى تم تعقيمها، ونمت لمرحلة البلوغ
and then released from planes all over the Southwest,
ومن ثم تمّ اطلاقها من الطائرات في كل أنحاء الجنوب الغربي،
the Southeast and down into Mexico and into Central America
والجنوب الشرقي وصولًا إلى المكسيك وأمريكا الوسطى
literally by the hundreds of millions from little airplanes,
وبالتحديد بواسطة مئات الملايين من الطائرات الصغيرة،
eventually eliminating that terrible insect pest
للقضاء نهائيًا على آفة الحشرة المدمرة
for most of the Western Hemisphere.
لمعظم نصف الكرة الأرضية الغربي.
Our real purpose in writing this editorial
هدفنا الحقيقي من كتابة هذه الافتتاحية
was to introduce readers to how we can do that today --
كان لتعريف القراء كيف يمكننا القيام بذلك اليوم
not with radiation but with our knowledge of genetics.
ليس عن طريق الإشعاع، ولكن بمعرفتنا بعلم الوراثة.
Let me explain.
دعوني أشرح لكم.
This is the bad guy: Aedes aegypti.
هذا هو الكائن الضار، الزاعجة المصرية أو بعوضة الحمى الصفراء.
It's the most common insect vector of diseases,
إنها من أكثر الحشرات الشائعة الناقلة للأمراض،
not just Zika but dengue, Chikungunya, West Nile virus
ليس فيروس زيكا فقط، ولكن فيروس الضنك، وشيكونغونيا وفيروس غرب النيل
and that ancient plague, yellow fever.
وذلك الوباء القديم الطاعون والحمى الصفراء.
It's an urban mosquito,
إنها بعوضة حضرية،
and it's the female that does the dirty work.
إنها أنثى البعوض التي تقوم بالعمل القذر.
She bites to get a blood meal to feed her offspring.
تلدغُ للحصول على وجبة دم لتغذية ذريتها.
Males don't bite; they don't even have the mouth parts to bite.
ذكور البعوض لا تلدغُ فهم حتى ليس لديهم أجزاء الفم للدغ.
A little British company called Oxitec genetically modified that mosquito
قامت شركة بريطانية صغير تسمى (أوكسيتيك) بتعديل هذه البعوضة وراثيًا
so that when it mates with a wild female, its eggs don't develop to adulthood.
بحيث عندما تتزاوج مع أنثى جامحة لا ينمو بيضها لمرحلة البلوغ.
Let me show you.
دعوني أريكم ذلك.
This is the normal reproductive cycle.
هذه هي دورة الإنجاب الطبيعية.
Oxitec designed the mosquito so that when the male mates with the wild female
صممت (أوكسيتيك) البعوضة بحيث عندما يتزواج الذكر بالأنثى الجامحة
the eggs don't develop.
لا تنمو البيوض.
Sounds impossible?
يبدو الأمر مستحيلًا!
Well let me show you just diagrammatically how they do it.
حسنًا، دعوني أريكم كيف قاموا بذلك بصورة بيانية فقط.
Now this represents the nucleus of a mosquito cell,
الآن يمثلُ ذلك نواة خلية البعوضة،
and that tangle in the middle represents its genome,
ويمثلُ التشابك في الوسط محتواها الوراثي، أو الجينيوم،
the sum total of its genes.
المجموع الكلي للجينيات الوراثية.
Scientists added a single gene
أضاف العلماء جينًا واحدًا فقط
that codes for a protein represented by this orange ball
الذي يتحول إلى بروتين ممثلٍ بهذه الكرة البرتقالية
that feeds back on itself to keep cranking out more of that protein.
التي تتغذى على نفسها للمحافظة على إنتاج المزيد من البروتين.
The extra copies, however, go and gum up the mosquitoes' genes,
غير أن النسخ الإضافية تذهبُ وتتلف جينات البعوض،
killing the organism.
وتقتلُ الكائنات الحية.
To keep it alive in the laboratory they use a compound called tetracycline.
وللمحافظة عليها حية في المختبر، يستخدمون مركبا لمضاد حيوي يدعى تتراسايكلن.
Tetracycline shuts off that gene and allows normal development.
يغلقُ التتراسايكلن عمل ذلك الجين ويسمحُ بالنمو الطبيعي.
They added another little wrinkle so that they could study what happens.
وأضافوا تجعيدة أخرى صغيرة لكي يستطيعوا دراسة ما الذي يجري.
And that is they added a gene that makes the insect glow under UV light
فقد أضافوا جينًا يجعل الحشرات تتوهج تحت ضوء الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
so that when they released it they could follow exactly how far it went
لذلك عندما أطلقوا سراحها، كان بإمكانهم تتبع مسيرتها تمامًا
how long it lived and all of the kinds of data
كم من الوقت تعيش وكل أنواع البيانات
for a good scientific study.
من أجل دراسة علمية جيدة.
Now this is the pupal stage, and at this stage
الآن، هذه هي طور الشرنقة، وفي هذه المرحلة
the females are larger than the males.
الإناث أكبر من الذكور.
That allows them to sort them into the males and the females
مما سمح لهم تصنيفها كذكور وإناث
and they allow only the males to grow to adulthood.
وسمحوا للذكور فقط للنمو حتى مرحلة البلوغ.
And let me remind you that males don't bite.
واسمحوا لي بتذكيركم بأن الذكور لا تلدغ.
From there it's pretty simple.
من هناك، فإن الأمر بسيط جدًا.
They take beakers full of male mosquitoes,
أخذوا كؤوسًا مليئة بذكور البعوض،
load them into milk cartons, and drive around the city,
حملوها في باكيتات حليب، وقادوا حول المدينة
releasing them guided by GPS.
وأطلقوا سراحهم بتوجيه من قبل نظام التموضع العالمي(GPS).
Here's the mayor of a city releasing the first batch
يطلقُ حاكم المدينة هنا أول دفعة
of what they call the "friendly Aedes."
لما أطلقوا عليه اسم (المزعجة الصديقة).
Now I wish I could tell you this is an American city, but it's not.
أتمنى أن أقول لكم بأن المدينة أمريكية، إنها ليست كذلك.
It's Piracicaba, Brazil.
إنها مدينة (بيراسكابا في البرازيل).
The amazing thing is that in just a year
والشيء المدهش هو أنه في عام فقط
it brought down the cases of dengue by 91 percent.
انخفض عدد حالات حمى الضنك بــنسبة 91%.
That's better than any insecticide spraying can do.
وهذا أفضل مما يمكن أن يقوم به أي رش للمبيد الحشري.
So why aren't we using this remarkable biological control in the US?
فلماذا لا نستخدم هذا الضابط البيولوجي الرائع في الولايات الأمريكية؟
That's because it's a GMO: a genetically modified organism.
السبب لأنه كائن معدّل وراثيًا (GMO).
Notice the subtitle here says if the FDA would let them
لاحظوا العنوان الفرعي هنا يقول، لو سمحت لهم إدارة الغذاء والدواء (ِFDA)
they could do the same thing here, when Zika arrives.
سيقومون بعمل نفس الشيء هنا عندما يصل زيكا.
And of course it has arrived.
وبطبيعة الحال قد وصل.
So now I have to tell you the short form
الآن، ينبغي أن أقول لكم الصيغة المختصرة
of the long, torturous story of GM regulation in the US
للقصة الطويلة، المؤلمة المتعلقة بتنظيم التعديل الوراثي في أمريكا
In the US, there are three agencies that regulate genetically modified organisms:
في أمريكا، يوجد ثلاث وكالات تنظمُ الكائنات المعدلة وراثيًا:
the FDA, the Food and Drug Administration,
إدارة الغذاء والدواء (FDA)،
the EPA, the Environmental Protection Agency,
ووكالة حماية البيئة (EPA)،
and the USDA, US Department of Agriculture.
ووزارة الزراعة الأمريكية (USDA).
Took these folks two years to decide that it would be the FDA
استغرق الجهات الثلاث عامين لتقرير أن على إدارة الغذاء والدواء
that would regulate the genetically modified mosquito.
تنظيم قضية البعوض المعدّل وراثيًا.
And they would do it as a new animal drug, if that makes any sense.
على أن يقوموا بها كدواء جديد للحيوانات، إذا بدا ذلك ذو معنى أو منطقيًا.
Took them another five years going back and forth and back and forth
واستغرق ذلك خمس سنوات أخرى ذهابًا وإيابًا ومرة تلو المرة
to convince the FDA that this would not harm people,
لإقناع إدرة الغذاء والدواء بأن هذا لن يضر البشر،
and it would not harm the environment.
ولن يضر البيئة.
They finally gave them, this summer, permission to run a little test
وفي نهاية المطاف، وفي هذا الصيف، أعطوهم تصريحًا بإجراء اختبار صغير
in the Florida Keys,
في منطقة فلوريدا كيز،
where they had been invited years earlier when they Keys had an outbreak of dengue.
حيث قد تم دعوتهم قبل سنوات عندما كان لدى (كيز) انتشارًا لحمى الضنك.
Would that it were that easy.
يا ليت كان ذلك بهذه السهولة!
When the local residents heard
عندما سمع المواطنون المحليون
that there would be genetically modified mosquitoes tested in their community
بانه سيتمُ إجراء اختبارات لبعوض معدّل وراثيًا في مجتمعهم
some of them began to organize protests.
بدأ البعض منهم في تنظيم احتجاجات.
They even organized a petition on the internet with this cuddly logo,
حتى أنهم نظموا عريضة عبر الإنترنت مع شعار يظهرُ الحب والمودة
which eventually accumulated some 160,000 signatures
الذي جمع في النهاية حوالي 16,000 توقيعًا
And they demanded a referendum
وطالبوا باستفتاء شعبي
which will be conducted in just a couple of weeks
والذي سيتمُ إجراءه في غضون عدة أسابيع
about whether the trials would be permitted at all.
حول ما إذا سيسمح بإجراء التجارب أصلًا.
Well it's Miami that really needs these better ways of controlling insects.
حسنًا، إنها (ميامي) التي تحتاجُ حقًا هذه الوسائل للسيطرة على الحشرات.
And there the attitudes are changing.
وهناك مواقف تتغير.
In fact, very recently a bipartisan group of more than 60 legislators
في الحقيقة، مؤخرًا، مجموعة من الحزبين مكونة من أكثر من 60 مشرعًا
wrote to HHS Secretary Sylvia Burwell
كتبت إلى وزيرة الصحة والخدمات البشرية، (سيلفيا بورويل)
asking that she, at the Federal level, expedite access for Florida
تطالبها، على المستوى الاتحادي، تسريع حصول فلوريدا،
to this new technology.
على هذه التقنية الحديثة،
So the bottom line is this:
فالخلاصة هي،
biological control of harmful insects
السيطرة البيولوجية للحشرات الضارة
can be both more effective and very much more environmentally friendly
يمكنها أن تكون على حدٍ سواء فعالة أكثر، وصديقة للبيئة بشكلٍ أكبر
than using insecticides, which are toxic chemicals.
من استخدام المبيدات الحشرية، والتي هي كيماويات سامة.
That was true in Rachel Carson's time; it's true today.
كان ذلك صحيحًا في زمن راشيل كارسون، وهذا صحيح اليوم.
What's different is that we have enormously more information
الشيء المختلف هو أنه لدينا المزيد من المعلومات الهائلة
about genetics than we had then,
حول علم الوراثة أكثر مما كان لدينا سابقًا،
and therefore more ability to use that information
وبالتالي المزيد من القدرة لاستخدام تلك المعلومات
to affect these biological controls.
للتأثير في هذه الضوابط البيولوجية.
And I hope that what I've done is aroused your curiosity enough
وآملُ أن ما قمتُ به آثار فضولكم بما فيه الكفاية
to start your own inquiry -- not into just GM mosquitoes
لبدء تحقيقاتكم الخاصة، ليس فقط نحو البعوض المعدّل وراثيًا
but to the other genetically modified organisms that are so controversial today.
ولكن لغيرها من الكائنات المعدّلة وراثيًا المثيرة للجدل اليوم.
I think if you do that, and you dig down through all of the misinformation,
أعتقد لو قمتم بذلك، وبحثتم في أعماق كل المعلومات المضللة،
and the marketing
والتسويق،
on the part of the organic food industry and the Greenpeaces
من جانب صناعة الغذاء العضوي ومنظمة السلام الأخضر
and find the science, the accurate science,
وعثرتم على العلم، العلم الدقيق
you'll be surprised and pleased.
ستدهشون وتسرون.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)